Guide to the Phelps Putnam Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Phelps Putnam papers
1914-1951
YCAL MSS 429
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.21
(13 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The Phelps Putnam papers contain correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and work of poet Howard Phelps Putnam. Correspondence in the collection features letters with family, Yale college friends, including Russell Cheney, Farwell Knapp, Donald Ogden Stewart, and Charles Walker, and other authors, including Paul Rosenfeld, Allen Tate, and Stark Young. Writings contains drafts for poems and short prose pieces dating from 1914 to the late 1940s. Other materials in the collection include biographical notes, clippings relating to Putnam, a last will, photographs, and a remembrance by his wife Una (Fayerweather) Putnam.
Putnam, Phelps, 1894-1948
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Walker, 1951. Additional gifts and purchases acquired from 1953 to 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Howard Phelps Putnam (1894-1948)
Born in Massachusetts in 1894, Putnam attended Philips Exeter Academy before enrolling at Yale. A member of the secret society Skull and Bones, Putnam has been named among the Renaissance generation at Yale, which includes Stephen Vincent Benét, Henry R. Luce, Archibald MacLeish, Cole Porter, and Thornton Wilder. Following graduation, Putnam traveled to Europe and worked a series of jobs, including a period as an assistant editor for The Atlantic Monthly Press and writing advertising copy for an insurance company. Putnam's first book of poems, Trinc, was published in 1927. Following publication of Trinc, Putnam set to work on an epic, to be titled "The Earthly Comedy," which would recount modern life and feature characters such as Bill Williams and his alter ego Bigelow Hasbrouck. The publication of The Five Seasons (1931) features these characters and marks the beginning of Putnam's work towards producing "The Earthly Comedy". Putnam never completed the work before his death in 1948, however, thwarted perhaps by ill health (asthma and alcoholism) and the paralyzing ambition of his plans. As F.O. Matthiessen acknowledges in his essay "To the Memory of Phelps Putnam," "he sketched a poem too vast ever to be able to shoulder the weight of writing it".
Putnam married twice, to Ruth Peters and Una Fayerweather, and had numerous affairs, including trysts with Katharine Hepburn and painter Russell Cheney.
Summary information on Howard Phelps Putnam taken from an October 2007 description of the Farwell Knapp Papers in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library poetry blog (see http://beineckepoetry.wordpress.com/2007/10/).
Scope and Contents
The Phelps Putnam papers contain correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and work of poet Howard Phelps Putnam. Correspondence in the collection features letters to and from family, Yale college friends, including Russell Cheney, Farwell Knapp, Donald Ogden Stewart, and Charles Walker, and other authors, including Paul Rosenfeld, Allen Tate, and Stark Young. Writings contains drafts for poems and short prose pieces dating from 1914 to the late 1940s. Other materials in the collection include biographical notes, clippings relating to Putnam, a last will, photographs, and a remembrance by his wife Una (Fayerweather) Putnam.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1915-1951. II. Writings, 1914-1947. III. Personal Papers, 1923-1946.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors; Knapp, Farwell, 1893-1942; Putnam, Phelps, 1894-1948; Putnam, Una; Cheney, Russell, 1881-1945; Rosenfeld, Paul, 1890-1946; Young, Stark, 1881-1963; Stewart, Donald Ogden, 1894-1980; Tate, Allen, 1899-1979; Walker, Charles R. (Charles Rumford), 1893-1974
- Correspondence, 1915-1951; Series I; 3.55; (9 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, features correspondence with Yale college friends Russell Cheney, Farwell Knapp, Donald Ogden Stewart, and Charles Walker, and with family and other authors, including Paul Rosenfeld, Allen Tate, and Stark Young.
  Unsorted correspondence is located at the end of the alphabetical run.
  - Agee, James, 1932, undated (Box 1)
  - Austin, Mary, 1930, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Bellinger, Alfred, 1916-1919 (Box 1)
  - Benét, Stephen Vincent, 1920, undated (Box 1)
  - Benét, William Rose, 1929 December 6 (Box 1)
  - Beston, Henry, 1927-1946, undated (Box 1)
  - Bynner, H.Witter, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Cheney, Russell, 1916-1931; 6 (Box 1)
    Includes photographs
  - Cheney, Russell, 1931-1945, undated; 4 (Box 2)
  - Cheney, Russell (outgoing), 1916-1918; 3 (Box 2)
  - Cheney, Russell (outgoing), 1919-1932; 9 (Box 3)
  - Cheney, Russell (outgoing), 1932-1941; 5 (Box 4)
  - Cutting, Bronson, 1930-1933; 2 (Box 4)
  - Darling, A. B., 1916-1927, undated (Box 4)
  - Davenport, Marcia, 1928 (Box 4)
  - Davenport, Russell, 1931-1947 (Box 4)
  - Draper, Muriel, 1930, undated (Box 4)
  - Eliot, T. S., 1927 (Box 5)
  - Farrar, John, 1917-1930, undated (Box 5)
  - Foster, E. [W.?], 1934-1945 (Box 5)
  - Head, James L., 1919-1928 (Box 5)
  - Howe, M. A., 1927 September 18 (Box 5)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1930-1949 (Box 5)
  - Johnstone, H. W., 1917-1918 (Box 5)
  - Knapp, Farwell, 1917-1942, undated; 4 (Box 5)
  - Kobbé, Philip, 1927 (Box 5)
  - Kreymborg, Alfred, 1928-1944 (Box 5)
  - Lytle, Andrew N., 1932-1933, undated (Box 5)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1932-1945, undated (Box 6)
  - [Manning?], 1937-1947 (Box 6)
  - Masefield, John, 1916-1921 (Box 6)
  - Matthiessen, F. O., 1928-1947 (Box 6)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1927, 1935 (Box 6)
  - Munger, Robert L., 1920-1928, undated (Box 6)
  - Oler, Wesley, M., 1916-1944 (Box 6)
  - Parker, Dorothy, 1930 (Box 6)
  - Perkins, Maxwell, 1929-1944 (Box 6)
  - Putnam family (outgoing), 1913-1937; 2 (Box 6)
  - Putnam, Una (wife) (outgoing), 1930-1951, undated (Box 6)
  - Rosenfeld, Paul, 1927-1938; 3 (Box 7)
  - Roth, Samuel, 1928 January (Box 7)
  - Shepard, D. C., 1916-1920 (Box 7)
  - Spencer, Theodore, 1927 October 13 (Box 7)
  - Stewart, Donald Ogden, 1916-1944, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - Tate, Allen, 1929-1946, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - Tate, Allen (outgoing) (photocopies), undated (Box 8)
  - Tener, George E., 1916-1920 (Box 8)
  - Troxell, Gilbert McCoy, 1916-1943, undated (Box 8)
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1927-1928 (Box 8)
  - Walker, Charles, 1917-1944; 3 (Box 8)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, 1935, 1938 (Box 8)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1927-1939 (Box 8)
  - Wolf, Max, 1941-1947, undated (Box 8)
    Includes clippings
  - Young, Stark, 1915-1927; 2 (Box 8)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1916-1950, undated; 4 (Box 9)
- Writings, 1914-1947; Series II; 1.58; (4 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries, for poetry and prose, and arranged alphabetically by title (in quotes) or supplied heading (in brackets).
  Series II, Writings, contains drafts, most corrected, for poems and short prose pieces. In additon to the title, physical formats (e.g. "holograph" and "typescript" ) are noted in folder headings below.
  Unsorted poems can be found under the supplied heading [Poems] and at the end of the alphabetical run of titles.
  - Poetry
    - "100th Anniversary About Women," holograph, undated (Box 10)
    - "About Women," typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - "Address to the Fighting Forces," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - "The Africa-Livingston Case," holograph, undated (Box 10)
    - "Alice and Beatrice," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - "Another Poem," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - "At Twenty," drafts, holograph and typescript, and printed version, 1914 (Box 10)
    - "Authors Write Books," typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - "Before the Lilacs Bloomed, " holograph, undated (Box 10)
    - "Bill," notes, holograph, undated; 8 (Box 10)
    - "Bill Williams," holograph, undated (Box 10)
    - "Bill Williams," notebooks, holograph, undated; 7 (Box 10)
    - "Byron, Lord, Jr.," holograph, undated (Box 10)
    - "Carlo Tresca," holograph and typescript, 1943 February 16 (Box 10)
    - "Cause for Divorce," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - "Charles H. Roberts," holograph, undated (Box 10)
    - "Cheney," holograph, undated (Box 10)
    - "Concerning an Ancient American," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 10)
    - "Country Boy," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Cutting," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "The Daughters of the Sun," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "The Dawning," typescript, 1914 (Box 11)
    - "Death is the Very End," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "December 25, 1946," draft, holograph, and printed version, undated (Box 11)
    - "Dirge for Hart Crane," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Dirge for the Use of Men," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Discharged Patient," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Diving Helmet," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Encouragement to the Greeks," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Les Enfants Apres Pendus," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Estimate of the Situation," holograph, 1944 (Box 11)
    - "Fellow Traveller," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Folk-Tales," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "For MacLeish," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Frank, in Praise of," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Girl's Curse," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Greece," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Hamilton Hadley," holograph, 1940 December 31 (Box 11)
    - "Hands," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "He & She," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Hopeful Stuff," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Hymn," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "I Am an Atheist," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "I Am Feeling It Now," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "I Could Not Write These Songs No More," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Imitations," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Incident, 1946," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Indian Whistle," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Indolence, holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Insomnia," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Irony Enough," [notes?], holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "The Ivy," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Knapp," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Lament for the American Legion," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Letter From Jefferson to Lenin," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Lines," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "The Little Man," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "The Long Fulsome Lines," holograph and tyescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Luther," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Madame America as of 1943," typescript (Box 11)
    - "Marseillaise II," typescript, 1943 January (Box 11)
    - "Marseilles," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Middle Class: Which Side Are You On?" holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Moral Problems," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Morning Song," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "My Sisters," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "The Naked King," holograph and typescript, 1946 (Box 11)
    - "Note," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Note on Neutrons," draft, typescript, and printed version, undated (Box 11)
    - "Note to Col. McCormick," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Ode to Food," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Ode to Pain," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Ode to Work," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Oh say does that star spangled..." holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "On Drink," drafts, typescript, and printed version, undated (Box 11)
    - "On Reading the Contemporary Verse," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "On Being Dead," typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Opus 69," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Period Piece, 1932," holograph (Box 11)
    - "Pete & His Banjo," holograph, undated (Box 11)
    - "Playthings," draft, typescript, and printed version, 1915, undated (Box 11)
    - [Poems], 1938-1942, undated; 3 (Box 11)
    - [Poems], undated; 3 (Box 12)
    - "Poems," plan for a book of poetry, holograph, [1925?] (Box 12)
    - "Political Lyric," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Putnam Battle Cry," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "The Republican Picnic," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Safe Advice," holograph, [circa 1941] (Box 12)
    - "Sensations of a Modern American by Degrees," holograph, undated (Box 12)
    - "Ship of State and Grandpa," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Six Sonnets," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "So Long, George Cory," holograph, undated (Box 12)
    - "Soldiers' Marching Song," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Song for Poets and Betrayers," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Song of Grief," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Song of My [Heart?]," holograph, undated (Box 12)
    - "Song of Words," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Sonnet for Emily Bronte," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Sonnet for Ruth," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Sonnet for Spring, 1947," typescript (Box 12)
    - "Sonnet of a Troubador," typescript, 1915 December (Box 12)
    - "The Time of True Love," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "To My Old Friend," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "To Some Young Poet," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "To the Last Reader of These Letters of D114," holograph and typescript, 1918 September (Box 12)
    - "To the Memory of Yale College," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - Trinc, printed version, corrected, 1927 (Box 12)
    - "The Turquoise Ring," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Una," holograph and typescript, 1939 (Box 12)
    - "Violence," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Wallace," holograph, undated (Box 12)
    - "Yeats," holograph and typescript, 1936-1940, undated (Box 12)
    - "The Young Antiquity," typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Young Hasbrouck's Impractical Dog," typescript, 1939 (Box 12)
    - Unsorted manuscripts, holograph, undated (Box 12)
  - Prose
    - "A Defense of Suicide", undated (Box 13)
    - "Dog Story", undated (Box 13)
    - [Essays], undated (Box 13)
    - Hancock Life Insurance Company advertisements, undated (Box 13)
    - "Hasbrouck, Bigelow", undated (Box 13)
    - "Joseph Conrad: An Incident", undated (Box 13)
    - "Making Money in Magazines", undated (Box 13)
    - "Manufacturers of N.E.", undated (Box 13)
    - "Note of Moral Murder", undated (Box 13)
    - "Peter, the Fantast", undated (Box 13)
    - "Play," scenario, undated (Box 13)
    - "The Poem of Patricia", 1915 April (Box 13)
    - [Reviews], 1922-1925, undated (Box 13)
    - "Roscoe, the Clerk", undated (Box 13)
    - "Rosenfeld", 1947 (Box 13)
    - "Self-Accusation of Cowardice", undated (Box 13)
    - "Thousands Now Living Will Never Die", undated (Box 13)
    - "True History", undated (Box 13)
    - Unsorted writings, 1944, undated; 2 (Box 13)
- Personal Papers, 1923-1946; Series III; 7
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III, Personal Papers, includes biographical notes, clippings relating to Putnam, a last will, several photographs, and a remembrance by his wife Una (Fayerweather) Putnam.
  - Biographical notes, undated (Box 13)
  - Clippings, 1923-1945; 3 (Box 13)
  - Last will, 1946 July 5 (Box 13)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 13)
    Includes photographs of Phelps and Una Putnam, Bronson Cutting, and others
  - "Some Further Notes on Phelps Putnam By His Wife", undated (Box 13)
  - Work plans for unidentified work(s), undated
- Oversize, undated; 1
  - Work plans (In Series III), undated (Box 14 (Broadside))